<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts on PHP in the Wild</title>
        <link>https://zaimblog-669aa.web.app/posts/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Posts on PHP in the Wild</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2022 09:23:23 +0800</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://zaimblog-669aa.web.app/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>Laravel 8 Add Custom Class Facades</title>
            <link>https://zaimblog-669aa.web.app/posts/laravel-8-add-custom-class-facades/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2022 09:23:23 +0800</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://zaimblog-669aa.web.app/posts/laravel-8-add-custom-class-facades/</guid>
            <description>So, you are having a good time crafting your application using Laravel.
Not just that, you keep using the facade feature of existing classes.
As your application grows, somewhere in the timeline you will need to integrate custom services.
However&amp;hellip;
The facade feature has been convenient to you, so how do we turn our custom classes into facade?
Laravel, to the rescue! (again) Laravel is an extensible framework allowing you to plug in and out, disable here and there, configure now and then.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So, you are having a good time crafting your application using Laravel.</p>
<p>Not just that, you keep using the facade feature of existing classes.</p>
<p>As your application grows, somewhere in the timeline you will need to integrate custom services.</p>
<p><em>However</em>&hellip;</p>
<p>The facade feature has been convenient to you, so how do we turn our custom classes into facade?</p>
<h2 id="laravel-to-the-rescue-_again_">Laravel, to the rescue! (<em>again</em>)</h2>
<p>Laravel is an <em>extensible</em> framework allowing you to plug in and out, disable here and there, configure now and then. Basically, you&rsquo;re free to do as you wish.</p>
<p><a href="https://laravel.com/docs/9.x/facades">Facade</a> included.</p>
<h2 id="steps">Steps</h2>
<p>We&rsquo;ll make a custom <code>Payment</code> service and have facade available to the class.</p>
<h3 id="1-create-custom-class">1. Create Custom Class</h3>
<p>Personally, I&rsquo;ll create another folder <code>Services</code> in <code>App</code> directory.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-php" data-lang="php">// App/Services/Payment.php

namespace App\Services;

class Payment 
{
  public function test(): string
  {
    return &#39;Test&#39;;
  }
}
</code></pre></div><h3 id="2-create-custom-provider">2. Create Custom Provider</h3>
<p>Next, integrating the custom service will need Laravel to recognize the service. Always register your service as provider to keep the pattern clean.</p>
<p><code>php artisan make:provider ServiceProviders/PaymentProvider</code></p>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-php" data-lang="php">namespace App\Providers\ServiceProviders;

use App\Services\Payment;
use Illuminate\Support\ServiceProvider;

class PaymentProvider extends ServiceProvider
{
    /**
     * Register services.
     *
     * @return void
     */
    public function register()
    {
        $this-&gt;app-&gt;bind(&#39;payment&#39;, function () {
            return new Payment;
        });
    }
}

</code></pre></div><h3 id="3-create-custom-facade">3. Create Custom Facade</h3>
<p>As there is no command to quickly create a facade class, we&rsquo;ll need to manually create the file.
Below, I have created a <code>PaymentFacade.php</code> file in the <code>app/Services/Facades</code> directory. Create the directory if you have not done so.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-php" data-lang="php">namespace App\Services\Facades;

use Illuminate\Support\Facades\Facade;

class PaymentFacade extends Facade 
{
    protected static function getFacadeAccessor()
    {
        return &#39;payment&#39;;
    }
}
</code></pre></div><h3 id="4-register-provider-and-facade">4. Register Provider and Facade</h3>
<p>We&rsquo;ll have to register both provider and facade so Laravel can bind them to the application.</p>
<p>Edit your <code>config/app.php</code> to add your newly create provider and facade classes.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-php" data-lang="php">// config/app.php

&#39;providers&#39; =&gt; [
  ...
  App\Providers\EventServiceProvider::class,
  App\Providers\RouteServiceProvider::class,
  App\Providers\Services\PaymentProvider::class,
]

&#39;aliases&#39; =&gt; [
  ...
  &#39;Validator&#39; =&gt; Illuminate\Support\Facades\Validator::class,
  &#39;View&#39; =&gt; Illuminate\Support\Facades\View::class,
  &#39;Payment&#39; =&gt; App\Services\Facades\PaymentFacade::class,
]
</code></pre></div><h3 id="5-import-the-facade">5. Import the Facade</h3>
<p>Well done!</p>
<p>Your custom service class is now accessible as facade!</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-php" data-lang="php">// web.php

use Facades\App\Services\Payment;

Route::get(&#39;/check&#39;, function() {
  dd(Payment::test());
});

</code></pre></div><h3 id="result">Result</h3>

    <div style="width: 100%; text-align:center;">
        <img loading="lazy" width="100%" src="./img//facade.png"   />
    </div>


]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Welcome</title>
            <link>https://zaimblog-669aa.web.app/posts/welcome/</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 27 Feb 2022 00:50:16 +0800</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://zaimblog-669aa.web.app/posts/welcome/</guid>
            <description>Introduction Welcome.
This would be my first ever writing in this blog. Well, then, obviously I owe you an introduction.
My name is Muhammad Zaim, you can just call me Zaim for short.
A lean guy with average height of Malaysian men. I was born on the 90s, grew in Malaysia and codes a lot.
Career Early in my career, I was thought of working in the semiconductor industry. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t care less since I&amp;rsquo;m kinda working in some areas that actually included semiconductor (The CPU I used for programming for example).</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>Welcome.</p>
<p>This would be my first ever writing in this blog. Well, then, obviously I owe you an introduction.</p>
<p>My name is <strong>Muhammad Zaim</strong>, you can just call me <strong>Zaim</strong> for short.</p>
<p>A lean guy with average height of Malaysian men. I was born on the 90s, grew in Malaysia and codes a lot.</p>
<h2 id="career">Career</h2>
<p>Early in my career, I was thought of working in the semiconductor industry. I couldn&rsquo;t care less since I&rsquo;m kinda working in some areas that actually included semiconductor (The CPU I used for programming for example).</p>
<p>I was yearning to work for companies like Intel or Celestica, because both are near to my hometown.</p>
<p>I took Computer Engineering course during my endeavours, that explained why I keep bragging about getting into the semiconductor industry from the start.</p>
<p>As I progress into the course, I found myself to be fond with software technologies. When I started learning about databases and Linux distributions during my studies, the topics was deeply immersed inside my head.</p>
<p>A more software-related courses ensued and I am keen to land a job doing software development. That&rsquo;s the summary of how I was so intrigued about softwares.</p>
<h2 id="what-i-do-exactly">What I Do Exactly?</h2>
<p>I do <em>programming</em> and stuff, particularly on <em>website development</em>. I found website as a piece of software that transcends across different devices and machines.</p>
<p>Making good and useful softwares have always been my priority and will always put me on shaky position if I could not deliver one.</p>
<p>I am also an <em>advocate of programming best practices</em>, simply means I will not take it lightly if I couldn&rsquo;t understand the code that I write without any further and thorough explanation about it.</p>
<p>Most of the time, I deal with PHP code and you could say I am familiar with the <strong>$$$</strong> 😎.</p>
<h2 id="past-works">Past Works</h2>
<p>I have done quite a number of projects in the past, you can check my <a href="https://github.com/zaimazhar">GitHub</a> account to check some of them.</p>
<p>Most of my monetary related projects are private, there could be nothing much expectation from freelancing projects. It is understandable, no business wants their competitors to get a look into their source code anyway.</p>
<h2 id="last-words">Last Words</h2>
<p>I appreciate if you made it to here, I am thankful with the journey I have went through from the start of the COVID-19 pandemic up to this point of my life. I have always stepped on the right rocks since, from meeting one random person to collaborate on a startup, to meeting a group of other developers, making money along the way, until I have landed a job as a software engineer.</p>
<p>I couldn&rsquo;t express the surreal feeling, it&rsquo;s like the path was paved little by little by Allah to make my life better by each day 🤲. I went through much, happy, sad, depress, everything.</p>
<p>I have met a lot of amazing people, and I want to apologize to any of them if I ever hurt them in any form. 🙏</p>
<p>I have nothing left to say, I&rsquo;ll left it on here and continue my writing later.</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4"><code class="language-php" data-lang="php">echo &#34;Thank you for reading my first blog!, have a nice day.&#34;;
</code></pre></div>]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
